Finding Aid for George Nicoloff Papers, 1935-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George Nicoloff Papers 1935-2004 1970-1990
Nicoloff, George.
05117 Aa 2
George Nicoloff was a priest active in the Macedonian/Bulgarian Orthodox Church in the Detroit area from 1936 to 1991, and was a lifelong supporter of the movement for freedom and independence in Macedonia. His papers include his own sermons and religious writings, as well as records, papers and correspondence from St. Clement and St. Paul, the parishes where he served, and the Bulgarian Orthodox Diocese of the United States and Canada.
3.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were donated to the library in 2005 by Mrs. Vera Nicoloff (Donor No. 8978 ). Additional materials have been received.
The collection is open to research.
George Nicoloff was born in 1906 in Sofia, Bulgaria. He entered seminary at the age of 13, and graduated 10 years later from the Theological Faculty of the University of Sofia. In 1930 he began doctoral studies in theology and philosophy at the University of Vienna. George Nicoloff and Vera Buneva were married in 1935. Shortly thereafter he was ordained to the priesthood and was selected to serve at St. Clement of Ohrid Macedono-Bulgarian Church of Detroit, where he first celebrated the liturgy in January of 1936.
While in Bulgaria, Fr. Nicoloff was well-known for his active role in the Macedonian Freedom Movement. He wrote for several newspapers and translated the Gettysburg Address from German into Bulgarian, the language in which he had it published for the first time. After his immigration to the United States, he became a leader in the U.S.-based Macedonian Patriotic Organization.
For nearly a decade after his arrival, Fr. Nicoloff was the only Bulgarian Orthodox Priest in the United States. He provided religious ministrations throughout the Midwest during this time period, and is estimated to have baptized, married, and buried thousands over the course of his career. Additionally, he served as a leader to the Macedonian/Bulgarian immigrant community, and helped many new immigrants establish their lives in this country. He was a frequent contributor to the Macedonian Tribune newspaper, as well as to the Voice of America radio broadcasts.
In 1970, the parish of St. Clement where Fr. Nicoloff served was moved to Dearborn Heights, where it became St. Paul Macedono-Bulgarian Orthodox Cathedral. In 1971, Fr. Nicoloff was elevated to Protopresbyter, the highest level attainable for a married priest in the Bulgarian Orthodox Church. He continued to serve actively at St. Paul until his retirement in 1991. Otets, as he was lovingly called by many, died in 1997 at the age of 90. In 2000, his family published a collection of remembrances of Fr. Nicoloff, a testament to the many lives he touched.
Please refer to the May, 15 1997 Special Edition of the Macedonian Tribune and the booklet In Remembrance of Father George in Box 1, which served as sources for this Biographical Note, for more detailed information on the life of Fr. Nicoloff.
The George Nicoloff papers document the activities of a Macedonian/Bulgarian religious and cultural community in the late 20th-century United States. The papers are divided into five series: Personal Papers, Planners, Correspondence, Parish Records (St. Clement Ohridsky, St. Paul Macedono-Bulgarian Orthodox Cathedral) and the Diocese series.
Most of the correspondence and many other documents in this collection are written in the Bulgarian Cyrillic alphabet, and so could not be assessed for content at the time of processing. Correspondence in Bulgarian is included either at the back of general correspondence folders, or, when it exists in sufficient quantity and can be separated from the main body of correspondence, in separate folders. Folders containing material principally in Bulgarian have been so noted.
Subjects:
Nicoloff, George.; Clergy.; Bulgarian Americans--Michigan.; Macedonian Americans--Michigan.; Macedonian Patriotic Organizations of the United States and Canada.; Orthodox Church in America. Bulgarian Diocese in U.S.A. & Canada.; Saint Paul Macedono-Bulgarian Orthodox Cathedral (Dearborn Heights, Mich.); St. Clement Ohridsky Church (Detroit, Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sermons.
- Personal Papers
  The Personal Papers series(1 linear foot) contains biographical information and records about Fr. Nicoloff, a few photographs, letters from church leaders, family correspondence, copies of religious items he wrote for the Voice of America and the Macedonian Tribune in the early 1980s, items published by the Macedonian Patriotic Organization of the U.S. and Canada, and records pertaining to the 30th and 50th anniversaries of Fr. Nicoloff's ordainment and marriage. It also contains information Fr. Nicoloff collected on immigration regulations, various Orthodox rites and customs, and the histories of the Macedonian/Bulgarian church and people.
  - Obituaries, newspaper articles, tributes. Mass card 1997, undated (Box 1)
  - Booklet In Remembrance of Father George, and compilation of letters of condolence and tribute, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Register book for Fr. George's memorial service 1997 (Box 1)
  - Bulgarian passport (1936), U.S. passport (1980), certificate of U.S. citizenship (1948), Efrosina Nicoloff's I.D. card (1936) (Box 1)
  - Marriage certificate and translation 1935, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Memoirs of Fr. George's mother Efrosina Nicoloff 1997 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, early 1930s, 1950s, 1961, 1980, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Promotion to Protopresbyter, Bulgarian Orthodox Church 1971 (Box 1)
  - Official lifting of Fr. George's defrockment 1991 (Box 1)
  - Memorial book for Fr. Vasil Mihailoff 1981 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Metropolitan Ambrosy and Metropolitan Sofrony 1939, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Family correspondence
    - 1935, 1937, 1960s (Box 1)
    - 1970s-1990s (Box 1)
  - Macedonian Patriotic Organization of the U.S. and Canada 1951, 1972, 1984, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Parish, Church and Ethnic histories 1959, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Information regarding immigration and U.S. citizenship 1970, 1978 undated (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, assorted ethnic and religious topics 1943, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Information on prayers, rites, sacraments, and services 1980-1982, undated (Box 1)
  - Photocopied excerpts from an encyclopedia about Macedonia 2004 (Box 1)
  - Articles written by Fr. George for Bulgarian-language publications 1929-1931, undated (Box 1)
  - "Voice of America" sermon transcripts (Bulgarian)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 1)
    - 1984, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Purchase orders for "Voice of America" transcripts from the U.S. information agency 1973-1976, 1984 (Box 1)
  - 25th wedding anniversary record book 1960 (Box 1)
  - 30th anniversary testimonial dinner 1965
    - Official invitation (Box 1)
    - Fr. George's address (Box 1)
    - Guestbook (Box 1)
    - Programs, biography, letter of thanks from Fr. George (Box 1)
    - Photographs (Box 1)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and logistical notes, including a letter from George Romney (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Bulgarian) (Box 1)
  - 50th anniversary celebration 1985
    - Photographs, program, mementos (Box 1)
    - Official congratulations from the Michigan Legislature (Box 1)
    - Letters of congratulations from politicians (Box 1)
    - Newspaper clippings 1985-1986 (Box 1)
    - Biographical sketch written by grandson George Nicoloff (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - Letters of request 1985 (Box 1)
    - Letters to news networks 1985 (Box 1)
    - Logistical planning (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous documents and correspondence (Bulgarian) 1969, 1975, 1976, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous legal papers regarding third parties 1924, 1941 (Box 1)
- Planners
  The Planners series (1 linear foot) contains annual planners and calendars used predominantly for the recording of events such as funerals, marriages, and baptisms, along with some more conventional diary entries.
  - 1942, 1943 (Box 2)
  - 1944, 1945, 1946, 1947 (Box 2)
  - 1948, 1949, 1961 (Box 2)
  - 1962, 1963, 1964, 1965 (Box 2)
  - 1966, 1967, 1968, 1969 (Box 2)
  - 1970, 1976 (Box 2)
  - 1977, 1978 (Box 2)
  - 1979 (2) and 1980 (Box 2)
  - 1981, 1982, 1983 (Box 2)
  - 1984, 1985, 1986 (Box 2)
  - 1987, 1988 (Box 2)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (.4 linear feet) contains correspondence pertaining to Fr. Nicoloff's activities as priest at St. Paul Macedono-Bulgarian Orthodox Cathedral and Diocese-related correspondence, as well as a number of letters from parishioners.
  - 1930s, 1946 (Box 3)
  - 1965-1969 (Box 3)
  - 1970-1975 (Box 3)
  - 1976-1978 (Box 3)
  - January-August 1979 (Box 3)
  - September-December 1979 (Box 3)
  - 1980-August 1981 (Box 3)
  - September-December 1981 (Box 3)
  - 1982 (Box 3)
  - January-August 1983 (Box 3)
  - September-December 1983 (Box 3)
  - 1984 (Box 3)
  - 1985-1987 (Box 3)
  - 1988-1989 (Box 3)
  - 1990-1991 (Box 3)
  - 1992, 1998, 2000 undated (Box 3)
- Parish Records
  The Parish Records series (.25 linear feet) contains newsletters, press clippings, photographs, documents pertaining to church committee meetings, and schedules of church events generated during the course of everyday Church business. Most of the records date from the time period between the move to Dearborn Heights in 1970 and Fr. Nicoloff's retirement in 1991.
  - St. Clement Ohridsky
    - Photographs of church groups and activities, 1938-1950s (Box 3)
    - Newspaper clippings 1942, 1960, 1963 undated (Box 3)
  - St. Paul Macedono-Bulgarian Orthodox Cathedral
    - Programs from ground breaking, consecration and dedication, and mortgage burning celebrations 1969, 1971, 1975 (Box 3)
    - By-laws and photographic directory 1972 circa 1995 (Box 3)
    - Newspaper clippings 1969, 1971, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Newsletters
      - 1971-1983 (Box 3)
      - 1984-1985 (Box 3)
      - 1986-1987 (Box 3)
      - 1988 (Box 3)
      - 1989 (Box 3)
      - 1990 (Box 3)
    - Church committee meeting minutes and annual reports 1970-1989 (Box 3)
    - Memorials 1979, 1981, 1984 (Box 3)
    - Easter programs 1972-1974, 1988-1989, undated (Box 3)
    - Holy week activity schedules and flyers 1974-1988 (Box 3)
    - Christmas programs and flyers 1981, undated (Box 3)
    - Sunday School 1979-1980, 1984-1985 (Box 3)
    - Dearborn-Dearborn Heights Inter-Faith Banquet 1972, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Mixed Bowling League Banquet 1981 (Box 3)
    - Usher instructions and assignment list undated (Box 3)
    - Orders for candelos, cencer, bishop chair, etc. 1971 (Box 3)
- Diocese: The Bulgarian Orthodox Church
  The Diocese series (.5 linear feet) contains records generated during the course of Fr. Nicoloff's work with the Bulgarian Diocese of the Orthodox Church in America. Many of the documents are related to the Diocesan annual conference, including Fr. Nicoloff's notes of the proceedings. Other documents include Diocesan publications, documents pertaining to local Orthodox organizations, and documents related to the split in the Bulgarian Orthodox Diocese in the United States in the 1960s.
  - Split in the Bulgarian Orthodox Diocese
    - Official documents 1963 undated (Box 3)
    - Documents, articles, notes (Bulgarian) 1956, 1958, 1960s (Box 3)
    - Newspaper articles 1963-1965 (Box 3)
    - Court case 1970 (Box 3)
    - Informational publications and letters to parishioners 1963, 1965 undated (Box 3)
  - Holy Synod reports 1969 (Box 3)
  - Diocesan Conferences
    - 1965, 1975, 1976, 1978 (Box 3)
    - 1979, 1980 (Box 3)
    - 1981, 1982 (Box 3)
    - 1983, 1984, 1985 (Box 3)
    - 1986, 1987 (Box 3)
    - 1988 (Box 3)
    - 1989, 1990, 1991, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Meeting minutes and notes for Diocesan organizations
    - 1979-1980 (Box 4)
    - 1981-1984 (Box 4)
    - 1985-1990 (Box 4)
  - Orthodox Church in America, All-American Council 1980 (Box 4)
  - Local Orthodox Organizations 1978, 1984, 1987, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Clergy Retreats 1979, 1982, 1983 (Box 4)
  - The Diocesan Messenger (Newsletter), 1977, 1979, 1981, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Archpastoral Christmas messages 1966-1988 (Box 4)
  - Autocephaly: a door to the future (pamphlet), undated (Box 4)
  - Programs from other churches 1979, 1980, 1984, 1991 undated (Box 4)